Guide to the William Robinson Papers, 1982-2002 AIS.2002.03
ULS Archives & Special Collections
William Robinson Papers
1982-2002
1997-2000
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Robinson, William R. (William Russell)
AIS.2002.03
8.75 Linear Feet (7 boxes)
This collection contains the papers of William Robinson and relate primarily to his involvement as an elected official serving the Hill District community of Pittsburgh in the Pennsylvania State House of Representatives. As a prominent member of the local African-American community Robinson was involved both politically and personally with a variety of race related initiatives and concerns. These records include correspondence, newsletters, clippings, meeting minutes, legislation, memorabilia, video tapes, and audio cassettes.
Biography
Lifelong Pittsburgh resident William Russell Robinson (1942-2020) has been actively involved in the political and educational process since 1974, and served as an elected official until 2015, representing Pittsburgh's Hill District.
From 1978 to 1985 Robinson served on the Pittsburgh City Council where he chaired the Committee on Planning Housing and Development, the Supplies Committee, and the Committee on Business Practices and Investment Policies. In 1988 Robinson was elected to the Pennsylvania House of Representatives where he served on the Appropriations, Intergovernmental Affairs, and Tourism and Recreational Development Committees. Robinson also served as the Democratic Chairman of the Subcommittee on Higher Education.
In 2002 William Robinson left the Pennsylvania House and would later serve as Adjunct Faculty at Carlow College and as a member of the Board of Trustees, Community College of Allegheny College, where he served Chair and Vice Chair. In addition, Robinson was as a member of the Allegheny County Council, until 2015.
Robinson was a graduate of Pittsburgh's Schenley High School (1960). He studied political science at Ohio State University, where he received a bachelor's degree (1964), followed by a master's degree from Duquesne University (1972).
Robinson died on June 9, 2020 in Pittsburgh at the age of 78 years.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection reflects William Robinson's work and achievements during his time as a member of the Pennsylvania House of Representatives serving the Hill District community of Pittsburgh, the 19th Legislative District of Pennsylvania.
The collection consists of six series. Series I consists of material related to the local outreach and community affiliations of William Robinson. Series II contains information regarding Pennsylvania state legislation and government affairs. Series III consists of material concerning African-American and minority issues, while Series IV relates to William Robinson campaign files. Series V contains information regarding William Robinson's website column and Series VI contains miscellaneous materials captured on videotape and audio cassette. Further notes are available at the series level.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of William Robinson, 2002.
Previous Citation
William Robinson Papers, 1982-2002, AIS.2002.03, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Allegheny County (Pa.) -- Politics and government; Pennsylvania -- Politics and government; Hill District (Pittsburgh, Pa.) -- Politics and government; African Americans -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Social action; African American politicians -- Pennsylvania; African American politicians -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Politics; Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Politics and government; Community College of Allegheny County; Robinson, William R. (William Russell); Pennsylvania. General Assembly. House of Representatives
- Local Outreach and Community Affiliations, 1993-2002; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  The bulk of Series I relates to Robinson's activities with the Soul Food Sampler event, a non-partisan picnic organized by Robinson for the constituents and business leaders of the 19th Congressional District, as well as Robinson's participation with the Community College of Allegheny County (CCAC) where he served on the Board of Trustees and was a member of the CCAC Finance Committee. The series also contains information relating to the University of Pittsburgh Jazz Seminar and Robinson's effort to secure funding and support for the construction of a new digital recording studio. This series contains correspondence, newspaper clippings, meeting minutes, budgets, announcements, memorabilia, and publications.
  - Soul Food Sampler, 1996-2002 (Box 1, Folder 1-11)
  - CCAC General, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 12-16)
  - CCAC Board of Trustees, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - CCAC Information Packet, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - CCAC Task Force, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - CCAC Budget and Funding, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - CCAC Education Foundation, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Report on Pennsylvania Community Colleges, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Association of Community College Trustees (ACCT), Annual Convention, San Fransisco, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Association of Community College Trustees (ACCT), Minority Affaris Conference, Biloxi, Mississippi, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - CCAC Health Care, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - University of Pittsburgh Jazz Seminar, 1997-1999 (Box 2, Folder 10-12)
  - Sgt. William H Carney Scholarship Committee, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - CCAC Community Legislative Initiatives, 1993-1995 (Box 2, Folder 14-17)
- Pennsylvania State Legislation and Government Affairs, 1994-1999; II.
  The bulk of series II concerns Pittsburgh stadium financing issues as they relate to Robinson's activities as a member of the Tourism and Recreational Development Committee in the Pennsylvania House of Representatives. Also included are gaming and gambling initiatives and files pertaining to Robinson government affairs in youth crime prevention, land value tax, and the financial records and correspondence surrounding Robinson's involvement with the Twenty-First Political Action Committee, a political organization developed to raise funds for candidate support. The series contains correspondence, news clippings, proposal outlines, financial statements, and publications.
  - Stadium Financing, 1998-1999 (Box 3, Folder 1-8)
  - Public Hearing: Public Financing of Sports Stadiums, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Regional Destination Financing Plan, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Committee Hearing on Stadium Financing, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Pittsburgh Pirates Stadium News Release, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Taxpayer Funding of Stadiums, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Democratic Policy Committee Hearing on Stadium Funding, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 14-15)
  - Regional Renaissance Legislation, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Stadium Forum Taskforce, 1998-1999 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Gaming and Gambling, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 18-19)
  - Allegheny County Affairs, Government Reorganization, 1995-1997 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Youth Crime Prevention, 1994-1995 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Twenty-First Political Action Committee (PAC), 1998-1999 (Box 3, Folder 22-26)
  - Land Value Tax Information, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence, 1995-1998 (Box 3, Folder 28)
- African-American and Minority Related Issues, 1982-2002; III.
  Series III contains information on African-American and Minority Related Issues. As a prominent member of the local African-American community Robinson was involved both politically and personally with a variety of race related initiatives and concerns. The bulk of the content relates to Robinson generated correspondence and advocacy for equal employment opportunities within the Pittsburgh Pirate organization and events surrounding the 1994 MLB All Star game. This series contains correspondence, newspaper clippings, newsletters, finances, and publications.
  - Black Elected Officials, 1997-1998 (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
  - NAACP Presidents, 1997-2000 (Box 4, Folder 4-5)
  - NAACP v. City of Philadelphia, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Opening of South African Consulate in Pittsburgh, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Negro Educational Emergency Drive (NEED) Endowment Fund, 1995-2002 (Box 4, Folder 8-10)
  - Economic Empowerment, 1994-1995 (Box 4, Folder 11-12)
  - Pittsburgh Pirate Ownership, 1994-1995 (Box 4, Folder 13-14)
  - 1994 MLB All Star Game, 1993-1995 (Box 4, Folder 15-17)
- Robinson Political Campaign Files, 1993-1999; IV.
  Series IV relates to William Robinson's Pennsylvania State House of Representatives political campaign efforts and contains correspondence, newspaper clippings, brochures, and campaign generated releases.
  - 1994 Campaign Files, 1993-1994 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
  - Local Candidate Support, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - 1995 Campaign Files, 1994-1995 (Box 5, Folder 4-8)
  - Bill Lloyd For Auditor General, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Delegate to Democratic National Convention, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - 1996 Campaign Files, 1995-1996 (Box 5, Folder 11-13)
  - 1999 Campaign Files, 1998-1999 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- "Bill's Book", 1997-2002; V.
  Between the years 1997-2002 William Robinson wrote a weekly column for his "Bill's Book" website addressing current issues of interest in Pennsylvania. This series contains the printed copies of William Robinson's website column.
  - "Bill's Book" Website Column, 1997-2002 (Box 5, Folder 15-19)
- Video and Audio Recordings, 1991-2002; VI.
  Series VI contains video content of Robinson guest appearances on the television program "Legislative Journal," footage from the 1997 Soul Food Sampler, public hearing tapings, and other recordings. The series also contains audio cassette recordings related to Pennsylvania House drug legislation debate.
  Note: All materials in this series are video tapes except for the last two which are audio tapes.
  - Legislative Journal, 1994-2002 (Box 6)
  - House Urban Affairs Committee Public Hearing on HB 2036 and HB 2059, 2000
  - Assault Weapons, 1993 (Box 7)
  - William Robinson Cable Program, 1993
  - Voter Registration, 1991
  - Impact Tape, 1994
  - Pennsylvania Legislative Black Caucus Mock Swearing in Ceremony, 1991
  - Soul Food Sampler, 1997
  - House Subcommittee on Higher Education Public Hearing on HR379, 1998
  - KDKA Newsmakers, William Robinson and Stadium Financing, 1998
  - House Democratic Policy Committee Racial Profiling, 1999
  - Legislative Meeting Standing Committee, 1999
  - "Night Talk" Racial Profiling and William Robinson, 1999
  - A Memorial Tribute to Gov. Robert P. Casey, 2000
  - Drug Legislation Debate, Hill House Association Tapes (Original and Copies), 1994
  - State and Local Government, William Robinson, 2002